Guide to the Thomas F. Lamb Papers, 1968-1974 AIS.1975.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thomas F. Lamb Papers
1968-1974
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Lamb, Thomas F.
AIS.1975.09
5 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
The collection of Thomas F. Lamb documents his political career as a Pennsylvania State Senator. The collection consists of general correspondence with constituents and records and correspondence relating to the Pennsylvania Legislative Reapportionment Commission, 1971-1973.
Biography
Thomas F. Lamb was born on October 22, 1922 in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, the son of James and Agnes Dunne Lamb. He attended St. James Elementary and High School and then went on to graduate from Duquesne University (B.A.) and Duquesne University Law School (LL.B.). Prior to his political career, Lamb served as Lieutenant in the United States Navy during World War II. He is a member of the Allegheny County and Pennsylvania Bar Associations. Lamb was also a member of many community organizations, which include Knights of Columbus, American Legion, V.F.W., and Knights of Equity. On October 5, 1957, he married Barbara Joyce and together they had four children, Thomas, James, Michael, and Barbara.
Lamb was elected as a Democrat to the Pennsylvania House of Representatives, 1958-1964. During his appointment to the House, Lamb was influential in making the University of Pittsburgh, which was nearing bankruptcy, a state-related institution. In 1966 he was elected to the 42nd district of the State Senate and was re-elected in 1970, in which he served until 1974. As the Democratic majority leader Lamb had a leading role in reaching legislative agreement in many debates. He was a supporter of mine subsidence, strip-mine control, and clean streams. Thomas Lamb also played a role in the creation of the Port Authority Transit (PAT), the establishment of college scholarship programs, and providing medical assistance for the poor. Lamb did not run for re-election in 1974 so he could spend more time with his family.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers of Thomas F. Lamb document his political career as Senator in the Pennsylvania House of Representatives during 1968-1974. The collection is comprised of two series contained in nine boxes. The first series is correspondence about a variety of social and political issues including abortion, civil rights, community affairs, education, and taxes. The correspondence series is arranged alphabetically by subject. The Pennsylvania Legislative Reapportionment Commission of 1971-1973 is the second series, which makes up the remainder of the collection. Included in this series are minutes of the commission, public hearing before the commission, and newspaper accounts of redistricting in 1972. Additionally, there is information regarding legislative reapportionment by county.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Thomas F. Lamb August 12, 1975.
Previous Citation
Thomas F. Lamb Papers, 1968-1974, AIS.1975.09, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Personal papers; Politics; Pennsylvania -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Legislators -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Lamb, Thomas F.; Pennsylvania. General Assembly. Senate; Pennsylvania. Legislative Reapportionment Commission
- Correspondence, 1968-1974; I.
  - Abortion (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aged (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agriculture, Game Fish (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appointments (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Auditing (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bicentennial, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Budget (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Business Commerce (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Civil Rights (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Civil Service (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Community Affairs (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Community Affairs: Kennedy, McKees Rocks, Moon, Robinson and Stowe Twps. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Constituent Problems, Complaints, etc. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Constitutional Amendment, 18 yr. old vote (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Consumer Protection (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Corrections, Bureau of (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Education General (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Education, Elementary/Secondary (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Education, Higher (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Education, Teachers (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Environmental Resources (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Federal Government (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - General Assembly (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Health Welfare (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Information, Requests for (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Interstate Relations (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Judiciary (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Labor Industry (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Legislative Action/Proposals (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Liquor Control (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Mental Health (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Military Affairs (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Mine Drainage Subsidence (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Public Utilities Commission (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Racing Commission (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Resolutions, Senate (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Taxes, General (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Taxes, Business (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Taxes, State Income (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Taxes, Sales (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Taxes, Senior Citizens (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Television (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Transportation (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Unemployment Compensation (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Pennsylvania, Legislative Reapportionment Commission, 1971-1973; II.
  - Minutes of Legislative Reapportionment Commission, 4.21.71-12.28.71 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Internal Correspondence of Legislative Reapportionment Commission, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Hearings Agenda (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Public Hearings before Legislative Reapportionment Commission, 12.14.71 12.20.71 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Preliminary Plan for Redistricting of Pennsylvania Senate by Legislative Reapportionment Commission, 11.17.71 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Constitutional Questions Concerning Length of Terms of State Senators after Reapportionment, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Reapportionment Arguments before the Supreme Court of Pennsylvania, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Reapportionment Arguments before United States District Court, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Newspaper Accounts of Redistricting and Court Decisions, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Reapportionment Maps (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Projections of Voting Trends in Senatorial Districts by Lockard Associates (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Pennsylvania Place Map District Listing 1970 Census of Population by Legislative Processing Center (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Population Statistics (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Senatorial Districts by Ward or Municipality with Population and Party Registration, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Reapportionment in the States: Alabama; California; Minnesota; New York; South Carolina Virginia, 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Senators' Residences by Ward and District (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Theories on Reapportionment (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Council of State Governments Publications on Reapportionment, January 1971- June 1972 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Misc. Correspondence regarding Reapportionment (Box 8, Folder 63)
- Legislative Reapportionment by County, III. (Box 9)
  - Allegheny (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Armstrong, Indiana Jefferson (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Beaver (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Berks (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Bucks (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Butler (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Centre (Box 9, Folder 70)
  - Chester (Box 9, Folder 71)
  - Crawford Erie (Box 9, Folder 72)
  - Cumberland (Box 9, Folder 73)
  - Dauphin (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Deleware (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Fayette (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - Fulton Franklin (Box 9, Folder 77)
  - Greene (Box 9, Folder 78)
  - Lackawanna (Box 9, Folder 79)
  - Lancaster (Box 9, Folder 80)
  - Lebanon (Box 9, Folder 81)
  - Luzerne (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Mercer (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Monroe Pike (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Montgomery (Box 9, Folder 85)
  - Northampton (Box 9, Folder 86)
  - Philadelphia (Box 9, Folder 87)
  - Schuykill (Box 9, Folder 88)
  - Venango (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Westmoreland (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - York (Box 9, Folder 91)